software engineering radio episode 103
10 years of agile with in Scala by this
is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se radio
prints irrelevant and detailed
discussions and interviews on soft
engineering topics every 10 days thanks
to our audience and the partners listed
on our web site for supporting the
porkchop
[Music]
welcome listeners to a new episode of
software engineering radio in this
episode we are going to talk to again
skully vibe about introduction of agile
development practices processes stuff
into projects and Arman's
companies we were you're also using a
new set of microphones which I just
wanted to mention because we've bought
them from your donations so please keep
them coming
ok so welcome everybody to show welcome
yen's welcome Marcus so why don't you
introduce yourself a little bit and give
us an overview of what you're doing and
why you're here today and talk about
this topic well I'm an independent
consultant from Munich in Germany and
I've started to use agile development
while I was doing consultancy for
object-oriented programming and design
and that was in 1998 and when I got into
contact with the ideas of well
lightweight process what we called at
that time and over time I figured out
that it is much more important really to
working at a way to be successful than
to know the details of object-oriented
development and so I started to switch
over and consult primarily in
introducing agile development into
organizations first into projects not
into organizations and learn from that
so our listeners probably knows some of
the HR development processes I don't
know XP crystal XYZ or scrum or
something which of those are you
typically working with and typically
using elements of all of them I think
all of these different methods are
actually views from different
perspectives on the same thing and the
same thing something like an agile
development there are some interesting
practices you can pick from each of them
especially the development practices you
can pick from extreme programming some
management practices you can pick from
scrum but I don't think that
development is something you take out of
the box and put into operation
anti-development is more a kind of
mindset for the management and for the
team and so introducing edger
development is much more than
introducing a new process it's
introducing a new mindset into an
organization it's it's interesting to
hear because other people when they talk
about XP basically say that you cannot
use practices from XP independent of
other practices because they all build
on each other so so it's interesting to
hear that you're picking some of them
and and using them in an otherwise
made-up process well some practices
belong together and you can't really
tear them apart you can't do any
refactoring without test-driven
development and you can't do test-driven
development without refactoring they
just belong together
other practices like the planning
practices are just optional so you can
still use for example user stories and
use cases for your analysis and then go
into an extreme stuff extreme start of
working so you have to know which
practices belong to each other and how
and the next problem is if you introduce
something you can't or it's well you can
but that's usually really hard and
there's a lot of resistance if you try
to introduce all of these practices at
once you may have teams that are really
fond of making frontier things and
trying that stuff but usually have to
introduce things step by step and so
that's a delicate balance you have to do
I guess there is also a difference
between more hands-on practices like
testing or refactoring and on the other
hand side more organizational
large-scale things and I guess for some
of well I guess you can do testing
without being officially in a natural
process so I guess this is another
distinction where it's probably
differently it's it's easier to
introduce some of them and not so easy
to introduce others I'm not sure about
that because all the practices no matter
how you fit them together in which you
take all the practices are actually
about
fast delivery over a long period so
enabling the team to deliver value very
fast but also to deliver very value for
years without getting into some mess and
this is more about mindset and if you
manage to get this mindset into the team
then the rest of the practice will
evolve over time that's just the way
they expect him did that at the grass
project what actually was kind XP was a
set of 12 practices out of about 50 they
used yeah okay so it's more or less
arbitrary well they could they did a
very good job being good practice out of
that but I've never seen two different
agile teams working the same way so it's
also about people working in there it's
about their organizational embedding of
the team yeah that's what I meant but
you know I thought that if you need if
you wanted if you decide to do whatever
six week iterations or four we get
durations and that means you have to
change the whole project structure yeah
you have to change the project structure
you have to even go down and change the
system of incentives you have an income
part mm-hmm and since he usually come to
one point where it's really hard to
change that the higher you get up in
management you won't always come up with
a perfect agile way to work okay so in
this episode we are going to focus on
going from traditional whatever that is
development processes to agile
development processes I mean based on
what you just said introducing agile
requires change so the challenge is not
so much to probably sustain an agile
development process one at once it's
probably implanted the problem is to
actually get there right why can't you
give us a little bit of an overview of
how to do this and then we'll step
through a couple of details well there
are actually 13 steps well no they're
not
the first thing you have to do is really
to understand how the team currently
works
um not these kind of consultants who
come in don't look at the team just say
okay he's the way to work and leave
again
and afterwards tell people I didn't work
and why it wasn't their fault right well
why it was their fault and of mine no
that's not my way of working so the
first step is really to understand the
culture of a team you go in and try to
understand what are the values and what
are values that keep you from being
agile Kent Beck once said all
methodology is driven by fear and so the
the basic question is how much fear is
there and why do people fear being late
because of some because they have this
record of always being late and so you
can address this fear and say okay if
you're afraid of being late why don't we
try to be much earlier than you thought
and when you're still late who cares if
you find some bad management practices
for example I had clients where they
were two managers were trying to fight
each other and were competing with each
other and the teams had to work together
and that did not work out so these are
things you have to address first and by
the way you still try to bring new
practices into that all the time if you
have a team that is very proud of his
current way of work you have to make
sure that you don't change the team of
the change team changes itself so you
don't impose changes could just suppose
changes if you have a team that is
currently working or looking for a new
way to work well then you can just say
okay here's one suggest and go
that-that-that-that and just try that so
it's about it's about convincing them
that they want to do it differently as a
pariah to coming with a book and say
read this that's the way to do it right
right I've never met a team that
would have liked to have someone coming
in and say okay everything you do is
crap do it that way and this one of the
problems if you have low qualified team
they're usually eager to change because
they see that it doesn't work but
they're still low qualified if you have
a very highly qualified team it's really
hard to tell them why should they show
change so either you have a team in
crisis then you're it's easy to change
but still well agile is not a silver
bullet or you still have to deal with
the crisis so you have to do much more
than introducing new process all you
have a team that really works in a
steady way of working and where the
management wants to improve some things
and the team says well we worked
successfully for 10 years why don't you
why should we change there's this
interesting research thing that I saw
once where various stakeholders in a
project were asked whether a project
that officially failed was a success or
not right and I probably know it so the
developers liked it because they could
learn all kinds of new technologies and
put it onto their CV and so everybody
had a different perception of whether
the project was a success or whether it
failed and why that's very interesting
quote from Thomas Edison who invented
the lightbulb right about right and he
was asked how could you bear failing
4,000 times before you've had your first
successful light bulbs and he said well
I did not fail I just eliminated two
ways that did not work and so the
approach to failure and the approach to
bugs you invariably do is one of the
things you have to change most teams
most developers are educated still today
that if you work good and sound and
scientific and blah blah blah that you
don't make mistakes
which is ok so we've prepared
and you've prepared a bunch of examples
right from your 10 year career in this
space and the plan is that we're going
to go through some of them and take
those take a look at the lessons learn
from them so the first one is called
basically a process professional I don't
know why it's called that way so
you give them an introduction about the
first example and and and what you learn
from it well the first example was the
team I learned how to work a trial
together with them mm-hmm
I came in there as an oo coach the team
had some experience with traditional
host style development cobol pl/1 that
was when which year that was in 1998 so
that's ten years ago and I came in with
the record of having crashed a project
where I imposed the style of working on
the routine so I knew what I didn't want
I didn't want to impose anything on them
what I really wanted to take their
experience and I also came in with some
ideas Alastair Coburn had implanted into
me about very short iterations by that
time very short iterations meant 8 to 12
weeks today I would call it duration 1
week but we started to learn at that
time so my tent was to get the team
together in a workshop and saying okay
we have this official our process of
your company which would conclude about
211 reviews before you were at the first
line of code but we don't need to follow
them what we can do is we just deliver
fast so we deliver after eight weeks and
think about the process together so we
have this workshop I call that process
workshop today we I would rather call
that retrospective yeah and although you
did that you did that at the beginning
and you here at respective at the end I
guess well you do reach respect to the
eff at the beginning of each new
iteration right but you have something
to look back at right yeah so what I did
there was I said okay look back at
bright projects you did by now you have
a lot of experience and collect anything
that made you faster
any practice you can think of any
support and collect anything that made
you slower and we put that on pin boards
and it took us about one day to set up a
process that was and that measures we
didn't have the word by that but it was
which was quite agile so they had very
close collaboration to the domain
experts we were lucky to have one domain
expert in the team full-time and the
others other developers were also
experiences the domain customer on-site
we that's domain expert on site which by
the way more really take a customer
whichever works well there is a bunch of
research on the customer role in XP and
I think it's one of the great ideas that
don't really work in fall so so let me
ask something briefly you said there was
this whole process with the 211 document
right you didn't have to follow it who
decided that did you have management
backing or was that just you decided
that's forget it we just proved that we
can do it differently well I thought we
had some management backing and the
basic idea here was this company was ISO
9000 compliant so how would you fit
something like that into an ISO 9000
compliant and the basic thing about ISO
9000 is that you have to have a
documented process to go to follow yeah
so I said we're going to declare the
first iteration as a prototype even in
the most ISO 9000 company a prototype
something you can do and you don't have
to follow the process and after that
process we're going to have an external
audit so I asked Alastair Coburn to do
an audit of that prods project and we
got an auditory part of about two
patrons saying well it's it's a great
way to work and here and there I would
suggest improvement and with this stuff
we went to the QA and said okay guys do
you really think we shouldn't do this
and well we have to
check that and whenever ready with
checking we heard about three iterations
running and the managers had this CD
with the system on their table and
eventually nobody really listened to Kay
anymore and by the way this saved the
life of the project several times so we
had this let's call it retrospective to
have it comply with today's terminology
we had this retrospective as the kind of
the driving power with every iteration
we did this retrospective at least for
two years and the team changed the
process but one of my favorite parts in
here was that in the first process there
was still of the design model so they
still said okay we want to do this wrap
design model using rational rows at the
end of the first iteration I came up and
said well guys I looked at this design
model we have it's still in the state
that it had when we started yeah oh yeah
we would have to update that and so they
updated this design model and after
second iteration I said at the end I
said well guys we still have this model
and it's still in the state at the end
of the first iteration and they said
well maybe if we have time we have to
update that and it took another
iteration until we officially cancelled
that because no one looked at that and
that was interesting experience I hadn't
worked without a design model before you
had not I I did not do that before that
was still at the times when John Roberts
was working at the small talk
refactoring browser and so we didn't
have these nitty gritty tools our clips
yeah no it no eclipse
complete you do what I mean at
mouse-click we didn't have that well we
had small talk which was it a small
topic yeah
the car was small talk we did some parts
in
and they see we did some small parts in
Pier one we later did some parts even in
Java but the car was a small talk and so
I had never worked without it is a model
and I learned I had to learn myself how
to work without a design model and that
was an interesting experience for me
because I had the learning experience
the team had the learning experience and
that prevented me from going faster than
the team and this is some of the
problems I still have to struggle today
I came in well I did lots and lots of
really complicated refactorings today
and you start with a team that has no
clue of all what we refactoring is about
well they know that he can rename a
method but they have no clue about this
experience when the design suddenly
starts to kind of or mess up design
suddenly starts to dilute and a clear
design emerges and so we hadn't had that
at that time and so I introduced some of
these techniques just like a submarine
we had this testing issues and I had a
little bit of experience with automated
testing so I downloaded what we at that
time called Kent Beck's testing
framework which was later transferred to
Java by confectionary , on him playing
Eric I blended in an episode before with
lots of whatever alcohol they undo like
i'm doodler I guess Austrian Airways but
that's just an aside well I do this
without I call actually whatever it was
let's go back to listen to this episode
I think it's 81 okay so today this is
known as s unit and this had two effects
on me it was one of the best pieces of a
small Takata ever seen so I had a lot of
learning experience about how to program
small talk me and on the other way I
said okay I want to just converting it I
want to do programming too
so I had one of my parts off the
critical path and I did that using this
testing framework
and I had some conversations with Paul
Tyson's at that time and he said well I
have seen this very interesting demo I
think it was a Kent Beck and Mike
feathers and they actually do
programming in the debugger and I
thought well that's a neat idea so I
started to do programming in the
debugger which works extremely well or
worked extremely well on small talk at
that time I've never experienced such
good debugger until now and so that was
the way I started with test-driven
development and I showed you some of the
other programmers well well I have this
test case and look here I just saved
this button and then we have this green
bar they say well oh well that's neat
and another one started writing tests
and so this idea of test-driven
development spread through the team like
cancer and when we did a retrospective I
think five years later they said without
the test-driven development we would
have failed
technically so this was actually our
backbone and anything else we could have
done it or not but this was this is a
thing so some of the lessons learned you
you learn from that project I think the
most important lessons lesson was really
to put the team into responsibility
which means two sides one really put the
decision up about the process on to them
and the other is make sure that they
also have to take the consequences this
idea of just starting with it
retrospective and doing that is
something I learned later is the also
the core idea of crystal clear so this
project is actually our learn later if
this project was one of the reference of
catalyst equipment for crystal clear
project which actually had the positive
part that I got a certification as
certified crystal practitioner
so this was one of the most important
lessons don't you ever run without real
perspectives and use the retrospectives
as the core tool to develop the process
you mentioned something that's actually
very important that is to develop the
process right I never talk about HR
processes because these are no processes
in the common sense common sense process
is something organization it poses on to
the teams if you work in an agile way
the process is proprietary of the team
so the team is allowed to change the
process whenever the thing that helps of
course they have to respect all the
forces on process which are also things
like reporting which is a collaboration
with other teams of the organization
yeah so like the external interface has
to be stable it has to be regarded it
doesn't need to be so ok necessarily but
you have to take care of that you must
not break the external indifference but
these are only parts of the forces and
the team is of responsibility of having
a good process and it's much more
important that the team identifies with
the process then that they stick to
certain rules because if they identify
with the process and someone does not
stick to the rules well either it's a
good idea because this strange guy
starts to do testing first and others
start to go on to that
that's like evolution or it's bad idea
so the team will start to look for the
consequences and say ok because you
changed this and that rule we had this
and that problem in the retrospective
so putting a lot of responsibility on to
the team are there any characteristics
the team must bring or have one thing
that comes to mind for example is a
certain level of motivation and
willingness to actually finish which
I've been in project well that wasn't
really the case they were all
demotivated actually didn't really care
about what's going on if they are
demotivated that's the first thing you
can work on and there's no process that
can make a demotivated team succeed you
first have to make sure the team works
as a team and then
can do right slaps right so
team-building measures is something you
have to do all the time and I have seen
really demotivated teams that started to
develop motivation once they saw they
could move something so you really have
to figure out where comes the D
motivation from and you have to work on
that if you can start with the D
motivated team but you can't succeed or
finish with it you motivate a team yeah
and the other thing well the motivation
is one important thing you have to care
about the other thing what I learned
that in that project was if you have
extensive rules process rules in an
organization that is not necessarily
something you have to give up you have
to be creative in working around them
you have to be creative you have you
really have to understand who imposes
this project process and why and one
thing that is really sexy
at least domain managers is success so
once the managers see that this C team
delivers results yeah posters becomes
much less important as you said it's
like fear or control imposed from the
external world and if they notice the
team works then they probably don't care
right and well some managers are more
relaxed about that some or less but I've
never seen manager of that would not
eventually give up to success yeah the
next project was what well it wasn't the
next one it was one I took out because
it wasn't it utterly failed okay okay
well the next project we're going to
talk about right well it was a software
company developing a product a team of
about 20 people the core development
team plus support and all the stuff
around that and they were in severe
trouble because people started to sue
them they had you mean legally legally
they had spent money for features they
never receive
there was nothing like a road map no way
the team could really deliver what they
promised
and so they said by the way we have very
little money so what is the least thing
you could do to help I'd almost think
about the success I had before I thought
well let's try to have just monthly
iterations and retrospectives well no
the complete team putting them into a
crop is too expensive for us at before
and so well but if you can help us do
the planning iteratively that would
really help so I was kind of tempted
because I didn't have too much time
anyhow at that time so I said okay let's
have two days a month of planning and
this planning sessions the chief
programmer was there and someone well we
would call product owner and the project
lead and the marketing guy and they were
sitting together and they had long lists
and what we actually did was we went
through this list prioritize them I told
them how to draw the water line so to do
the estimation on how much I can do for
one iteration and then after one month
we met again and they made some progress
and so I thought well this kind of works
and after another two months they came
up and said well we have this business
consulting consulting here and he said
this is not enough and thank you for
your work and he's going to do the
project lead and going to change
anything so what this guy was he set up
some kind of I think remodel or whatever
to my knowledge this company still
exists they still struggle and they're
still far away from working agile and
why do you think your attempt failed
well I think this other consultant was
right was too late and was too little of
change
so I shouldn't have gone in there with
just these very little drops yeah so you
have to do more than just meeting once a
month and help the team there is there's
a starting phase where you have to
implement the ideas well and where we
have to help the people to come over the
first obstacles is it also that the team
has to get the impression that you are
in the same boat with them like if you
are like full-time working for this
company your own caught salary depends
on the success if you just come there
like once or twice a month you know like
talk the nice talk and then go again you
might not have the necessary credibility
with a team well welcome full-time is
one way to become the quality time I
think the other thing is the developers
and the managers have to see success and
you have to spend enough time to enable
them focuses success I usually try to
have about two teams in parallel so I
rarely spend more than two to three days
a week with the team but that's enough
and you really have to stick with them
even if things get tough yeah if you
just lay back and so uh that's all your
fault yeah you're lost so you have to
have credibility but you don't need to
work full time okay then okay right so
the next example focuses on testerman
development yes I think that process
project because that was kind of a
completely different way I did not start
from the management perspective I did
not start from the process perspective I
started from the technical perspective
the background was was severely
struggling project it was I think it 200
person project one of these very large
things with financial service company
and they had forgotten a complete piece
of their architecture on which all the
other teams relied and all the other
team
were close to delivery they said well we
are going to be ready in three months
but only if this special piece of
architecture will be there in six months
weeks and no one had ever thought about
this piece of architecture because they
had thought they could buy it but they
couldn't because they had some very
tight requirements there and no of these
tools on the market were even able to go
near these requirements okay so the
eventually the responsible executive
figured out that they had a problem and
he knew that I had built stuff like that
before and so he called me in and I said
okay I'm doing this under one
precondition
I don't want to talk about process I
want to work this team the way I think
is right and this sub team it was only a
small team of three or four people who
took responsibility for this piece of
the architecture and anything that helps
them to deliver is okay I won't don't
want to have any discussions on ISO 9000
or CMM or whatever and he said well as
long as you deliver and we can't see
afterwards how you worked
anything is fine with me so I had kind
of process back up from upper management
the executive level and I immediately
start with them doing test-driven
development so what they had done was
kind of small prototype and they said
well this is some of the ideas and now
we start from the scratch end of this
thing right and I said no you have
something that at these kind of works
here we took two days to encapsulate or
back up that with test cases that was
one of the early Java projects so we
used a unit we back that up and then we
we started to refactor
they had into the direction we wanted to
have and as a result it took us well
eight weeks until we delivered the first
part of the architecture that was enough
for them to work they had lots and lots
of really strange requirements no one
had done before and so we said okay we
first were going to do what a standard
so you have the interface to work and
then we're going to talk about the rest
so what actually happened was after
eight weeks we are delivered they were
really surprised to see anyone deliver
because no one had delivered before at
least not working code and what else
could you deliver sort okay just to
clarify document ml diagrams we you
could pave the wall with tapestry of
your male models there but the a working
code actually was his minor thing in the
end
and they only was very waiting for us so
they could start and so they started and
well it wasn't four weeks it was
actually two years later that they
delivered the first code that could run
go into production so with this
component that they depended on yeah
well our component was running after
eight weeks irrelevant and the other
guys took another two years right yeah
and we then cut them down and said okay
what are the next steps for us we want
the next steps we can do for the next
four weeks and okay we're going to talk
later about these nitty-gritty
interesting academic stuff but what you
need for the next four weeks
and so we delivered that and in time I
think a little bit before time without
any severe arrow in there then they said
well you're not finished because you
have to write the documentation so we
said okay what is more important
documentation all this nitty-gritty
stuff and they said well this time we
really need the documentation and we
said okay we'll write documentation and
this really interesting academic stuff
never was built actually so what we had
done was we had stolen their most
important excuse for not deliver
and that was an interesting dynamic in
the team so what were the lessons
learned from there
one of the lessons was once the
programmers are infected with the
test-driven development they will go on
using that this team wanted to move on
using test-driven development when we
had finished that sub project they were
put to other parts of that product where
they did not use test one development at
all well they still have this waterfall
method of working and they try to
introduce test-driven development they
failed and they left the company and run
somewhere where it could they could use
test-driven development
so once developers are really infected
and had success with the test-driven
development there's no way back
[Music]
the other lesson was that the whole
organization did not change at all so if
you have a pure technical approach your
organization won't work or won't change
and that won't be a sustainable change
in other words if the environment
becomes ever associate material again so
you have to kind of change your external
interface in a way that's kind
incompatible with your agile team and
there's a problem right you really have
to change the organization around that
you have to change the management
mindset there's no such thing as a
purely technical driven approach to
introducing a development I would even
argue that that's true for whatever you
want to introduce on a technical level
as people might know I'm I'm like this
modern person and I always have the same
problem that I wanted to do certain
model driven things which is in some way
comparable to test driven it's a
technical aspect of the system of
building the system and if you don't if
you don't arrange for a suitable
environment and management and project
structure it's not going to be
successful well I think from a certain
level there are a management is
compatible with lots of technical
approaches if you use object-oriented
well or others or a procedure from a
certain management level this only
matters of ways of productivity so you
can change that from technique approach
things like model driven development so
agile these all have
social implications sure you will fail
if you don't do that what actually
happened here was well I think Gemma
Shriram Meszaros was the one who said
that if you kind can't change your
company you will change your company and
this is what the developers did yeah so
we succeeded and having a really
sustainable change with the developers
the company didn't change so the company
lost some of their best people yes so in
the last example you gave you you
present an example where you did not or
you weren't you weren't able or not it
wasn't necessary or whatever to change
your organization of of the that hosted
the project you just changed quote an
implementation detail which was in this
case testing the next example is the
opposite where the focus was on changing
the organization well it was a
medium-sized organization actually a
product supplier with about 60 people
working in there and I liked the heading
of that spaghetti alla chef because what
happened there was that the CEO still
programmed so this system was his baby
he was one of the I think brightest
persons I've ever met in terms of how
far he could understand new analytical
things but he was not really blessed
according setting of organizations so he
was a chaotic genius kind of that yeah
and he had set up these interesting
piece of software and they had
eventually found out that they were not
able to deal with all the bugs and new
requirements and so they had a huge
backlog and they had reacted to that by
hiring I think about ten new developers
there were three developers first and
they had ten new programmers and thought
that would self solve the problems and
after one year they had found that
things had even gone worse which is no
surprise and so they called me and
Johannes link and they said as well we
read this interesting stuff about XP and
so please do introduce XP now and so we
took about eight weeks to really
understand how this company works and we
figured out that they had very very deep
organizational issues everyone the
company was convinced that the
programmers were not working fast enough
there was no organized way how
requirements come from the client into
the product so they had these key
account managers and the key conventions
were fighting against each other to get
development resources and the
development itself was very crabby
because the code was spaghetti code very
traditional database driven spaghetti
code in C++ so we there was no planning
discipline at all on no level so we had
neither had strategic planning all that
did we have anything like release
planning or iterations just basically
went on in one big stream of hacking and
and so the first thing we did was to set
up a complete picture of the system and
saying okay
currently you think development is too
slow but the problem is not that
development is too slow the problem is
that development is not effective enough
you have too much bugs in there the
quality is way too low
there's no prioritization on terms of
what new requirements mean for the
company for the organization and all
that stuff is missing and so we're going
to do two things we're going to split
the development team into two parts one
team is going to start in an XP style
the other team is going to continue with
the way they were
they do start some test-driven
development when they think it's
appropriate but we're going to work with
the requirements process we're going to
work the key account managers so we
introduced weekly monthly and quarterly
iterations so we have weekly iterations
monthly increments quarterly releases
yeah we introduced the Kanban principle
of planning the what Kanban principle
which means you put the cards on the pin
board and the development team picks the
cards okay mm-hmm so you don't have a
push principle and running you have the
POE principle yeah and you just say okay
this is the amount of work you have to
do as a development yeah and it took the
development team about 3/4 of a year
until they really learned oh wow we have
the responsibility and we have to care
about it's not anymore that someone
tells us what to do and that was a major
change the key commanders had to learn
that it was not only development it took
us about well three weeks under the
development really came up to speed and
really delivered every week what was in
the plan it actually was the time we
figure out the velocity and once we have
the velocity we could do reliable
planner and the project manager said
well that's interesting we have plans we
could rely on but I was very mean I said
well no you don't rely on your plans
because all we have now is the velocity
for getting things into test but your
responsibility as key account managers
that's the way they were set up to test
that stuff and no one tests you throw in
all these red cars things the client
calls up that record duration planning
of the week but it takes you three weeks
to plan yeah so they got rid of all
these throwing in red cards going inside
of the planning they went into the plan
and about three months later I always
had this fight with the guys and all
this is the process you're going to
stick through that process
and about three weeks three months later
one of the key account manager said guys
and what the heck are we doing here
we're still fighting each other instead
of sitting together and really trying to
get out of this mess and figuring out
what is really important and put that
into with the you're talking about how
the velocity is calculated and I was
sitting there and saying well this guy
is doing my job great and it took
another month and I backed out of the
planning and started to concentrate more
on development in architecture and by
that time the second team that had
started to use XP
kind of got stuck it was from now we
probably imposed too much new stuff on
them we imposed test-driven development
on them we imposed c-sharp well this was
a Microsoft company so it was c-sharp we
we had used we imposed C shop of them
which wasn't you
we had to impose object or entities on
on them which they had no clue about and
we had used impose all these XP
practices and so it turned out that for
everything that failed XP was blamed and
we kind of sense this threat that the
organization would switch back because
this one project failed and so we stood
up and said to the executives okay guys
that was a nice try we thought that
would help
but for this and that and that reason we
think it's more appropriate to cancel
that project and have one development
team and help this development team to
come up to speed and this year was you
could have said well you are the one to
blame Angela blah blah blah and goodbye
and we were pretty much expecting that
but by the way we had enough of success
with the planning team and the clients
were calling up the manager and saying
well we were about to sue you but by now
we see something is changing and
if you keep on changing and if you keep
on doing reliable things and if your
quality evolves we're not going to sue
you so we had this success stream there
and we also could show some success with
XP team and we said okay these guys have
learned some stuff they have learned how
to set up fitness tests and so on so
let's start with putting an acceptance
test into the whole team because unit
tests were no way we had tried that and
so we were able to start do refactoring
test own development with some of these
developers and eventually that started
to spread we're not through with that by
now but we're still I think we are
pretty much through with changing the
mindset so all the organization is now
focused on delivering their focus on
delivering value to the customer and if
they fall back to old practices like
mustard not testing this stuff there
will be something or someone coming up
and saying okay guys we have to deliver
value yeah
and so with all the technical problems
they still have we do a lot of
refactoring and some of the most
frustrated entries in my blog about
refactoring you're protecting this
product right now yeah I write and oh
come from that project but I said to be
honest yesterday we are there's no land
inside by now but we have learnt to swim
and we're currently well they're our
first return on investments visible but
we're not quite sure whether this is
just because we tweaked the statistics
or whether so this took more than a year
by now and we I think it will take them
at least one more half to one year and
they still have to do significant
organizational changes until they really
run smoothly and are able to move on the
market and really do strategic
so what's what's it what is it you you
learn from this project I think the most
important thing is if you have lots and
lots of legacy code
you can't ignore that you can't just go
over and switch to other way of working
doesn't slows you down so much or it
slows you down you don't deliver value
anymore so what you have to do is a very
careful approach a combination of
cleaning up the code base on the most
important stuff setting up acceptance
testing from outside blackbox testing
changing the mindset changing the
planning organization and all that has
to be done at the same time
[Music]
but each of them is dependent on each
other so this is a very complicated
thing and this is actually something I
don't think you can do successfully just
by hiring someone who went to two day
course okay so I guess that was the list
of examples we have prepared right why
don't we sum up all this stuff and call
it a day
one of the lessons learned is reach
respects of the core of a chart fragment
which pretty much complies to what Elsa
says crystal clear is anything you do if
you do regular retrospectives if you do
is reach perspectives the team will
eventually start to identify and take
responsibility and go into a dry
practice there's another lesson is
there's no such thing as very light
coaching introduction you need to work
with the team at least two days a week
and you need to work on all levels you
need to work with a management you need
to work with the product management key
account management with a customer
representatives and you have to work
with the developers and the testing team
so you really have to have a whole
vertical slice I think it needs at least
six months
usually about 12 months until you have
enough momentum to let the team run to
keep it running
it's if you go and they continue to have
yeah to sustain a change to have a
sustainable change six months is
something are the the kind of horizon I
usually start with because after six
months you really know the team the team
though is you you say okay let's do that
as a trial period and after six months
we can see the direction enough momentum
is twelve eighteen months something
about that and usually have pretty fast
first success stories after one or two
iterations when the velocity is set and
people see that they actually do deliver
what they plan that you really have a
return investment is one to two years
and that is about the same time you need
until the development team is really
into it and doesn't know how to work
differently anymore infected if it's if
the virus is spread then you don't but
that takes time that's long incubation
and if agile development really works
for one or two years then I think it's
pretty robust against losing some
practices because if the team has enough
discipline to do regular retrospectives
that will kind of correct itself but you
need management support agile management
is one of the course if you don't change
the management attitude if you don't
change the way management thinks then
you're lost and you can't do it at a
development without Testament
development because if you do that if
you do this very fast iterations and you
don't do test-driven development and
refactoring yeah
then you will mess up your architecture
and you won't be able to sustain that
for longer than one or two years and the
last very important lesson I've learned
is
legacy code is one of the major impacts
on your interruption strategy and makes
introduction much more complicated and
takes much more time to use at your
development if you have a large base of
legacy code cool so I guess we need some
point a separate episode episode on how
to work with legacy code and we also
will have an episode by the way on
retrospectives with Linda rising we've
planned to do that at a Q Khan so that
should be cool yeah Linda is definitely
someone worth to listen to absolutely so
yes thank you very much for being on the
show you're welcome and see you later at
about P you later
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
SE - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for se radio for example by clicking on
the Digg reddit delicious and slash dog
buttons to contact the team leaves an
email to team and su radio net or if
it's specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license please see the website
for details thanks to Charlie crowd and
the pot site Music Network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas hard rock shuffle